This is Software Engineering Radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net.
SE Radio is brought to you by the IEEE
Computer Society and by IEEE Software
Magazine online at
computer.org/software.
>> [music]
>> Hi everyone, welcome to today's episode
of Software Engineering Radio. Our guest
is Mark Brooker, VPN Distinguished
Engineer at AWS, and our topic is
spec-driven development. If you tried to
use AI to write code, you've probably
noticed how productive AI coding can be,
but also that things start to break
pretty soon. Spec-driven development
aims to correct that. So, rather than
treating prompts as a main artifact, it
treats specs and intent as a source of
truth and uses them to drive the code,
the tests, and reviews. Welcome to the
show today, Mark. So great to have you
here. Is there anything you'd like to
add either to the topic or your bio
before we get started? Yeah, well, thank
you. Thanks for this opportunity to talk
about this topic. I've been building
software in various ways for the best
part of 30 years, maybe slightly over 30
years, and this is so exciting to have
this new set of tools in my toolbox as a
software engineer and as somebody who's
really interested in building software
and more broadly building systems to
serve customers with software. So, you
said you've been doing this, developing
software in different form or fashion
for a long time. Could you help us by
summarizing the current SDLC best
practices?
Yeah, well, I think obviously that
varies from organization to organization
and team to team, but the way that I see
that is when I think about a
high-performing software team, this is a
team that is iterating quickly. They're
very close to the customer in gathering
requirements. They're very close to the
business in gathering requirements.
They're working to get feedback from the
business and from the customer about
what they're building as quickly as
possible. Often they are operationally
close to running the things that they
are building, especially if they're
cloud services or software as a service,
and they are working closely across
multiple disciplines between software
teams, designers, product folks,
customer-facing folks, and so on. And we
can talk about get into the more kind of
software development part of that, but
for me it is really about structuring
teams and organizations to be able to
iterate quickly and be close to their
customers and close to their businesses
that lead to good outcomes for software
development.
So, you mentioned a lot about iteration
and feedback loops and structuring
teams. So, so far a lot of teams have
been aligned with the Scrum or similar
form of iterative dev process. As we
start to introduce AI into the mix, what
are the things that you have been
observing? Probably the biggest thing
that's changing is
the multiplier of overhead of process
goes up. It becomes so much more of a
big impact, right? And so, if I think
about, hey, I used to be spending 70% of
my time building software, actually just
writing code and testing code, writing
designs, and so on, and 30% of time on
overhead, if the speed of the software
building portion has gone up by 2x or
4x, let's say 2x, right? Now, I've
suddenly shifted the ratio from 70/30
to something that's closer to 50/50. And
so, as that software portion speeds up
or the code building portion speeds up,
so we also have to figure out how to
speed up the rest of the software
development process, or we don't get a
ton of the benefit. And so, that's been
this kind of second-order effect I've
seen with teams as they have embraced AI
and embraced the faster speed of coding
that have gone with that is they've also
had to pay a bunch of attention to how
do we build better processes? How do we
make those processes lightweight? How do
we use AI to accelerate a lot of those
processes? And that's something that
there's a ton of conversation around now
that I'm excited about. Then, I think
the other part of that is
another big enabler in taking advantage
of the speed of being able to build with
AI is having great infrastructure for
testing and for knowing if that code
works. And so, the teams that I've seen
get the best benefit from AI are the
teams who have made investments in test
infrastructure, in testing, in knowing
what their software should do, and
therefore can move really fast and move
really fast with confidence. You spent a
lot of time in focusing on all the
things that surround the actual writing
of the code. Though a lot of the hype in
the last year has been just on the
coding with wipe coding being a term
that nobody could not have
>> [laughter]
>> heard of. Yeah. How did you make that
journey or how did you observe
developers making the journey from wipe
coding to now understanding that's a
small part or not the whole part of the
whole experience?
I think that's something of a natural
journey. And so, I start off wipe coding
and it feels great, right? Like it feels
so productive and I get so much done and
I generate so much code, and then I
realize well, I've actually got to get
this out into production. You know, if I
want to have an impact on my business
and my customers, I've got to get it out
into production. Oh, now I need to be
able to test it. Now I need to be able
to validate it. Now I need to actually
be able to know that those features that
I built are the right features for the
customer. So, it's this natural thing
that happens to teams of saying, hey,
we're going to pick up these wipe coding
tools. It's going to feel great. We're
going to feel super productive. And then
the sort of and then happens. It's like,
and then, well, I need to maintain this
piece of software. I need to test this
piece of software. I need to listen to
customers and feedback in what they're
saying and improve the piece of
software. And that's where it becomes
really obvious that wipe coding, as
great as it feels and as useful a tool
as it can be, isn't everything and
doesn't solve the end-to-end software
life cycle. It solves a small part of
that or accelerates a small part of
that. And even if you accelerate that
substantially, you haven't yet
accelerated the whole end-to-end process
of what it takes to build a successful
software system. But if I'm building
something for my own use, little hobby
project, that's okay, right? It's fine
and I get a huge amount of the whole
end-to-end life cycle done just with
wipe coding. If I'm building a piece of
a critical service or an application
that I need to put in front of my
customers and meet a safety bar and a
security bar and a quality bar, well,
then I need something more. And even
more so, over the long term, if I need
to maintain that software for weeks,
months, years, decades, then I need a
more, let's say, sustainable process
than the one that this kind of pure wipe
coding approach offers me.
You mentioned maintaining a couple of
times and that's key. But what about
even reading the code before that? How
does that work? How do code reviews
work? Yeah, I think this is one of the
key questions that's being asked in the
industry right now is where do we go
with code reading? Where do we go with
code reviews? Code review from my
perspective has historically been this
incredibly useful tool for driving
software quality, for driving alignment,
for driving API quality. I'm not super
optimistic about it being a way of
preventing bugs, but I think it does
drive out quality. It does improve code
design and has these good outcomes. But
as we accelerate, well, what is the role
of that kind of code reading?
And I suspect where we're going to end
up with for a lot of code bases is, and
not all, but a lot, is code reading is
going to go a little bit of the same way
that reading assembly code did 50 years
ago. We're going to start building in
these high-level languages and people
are going to say, well, if you're going
to build in a high-level language, you
have to read the compiler output and
check it's right. And people did that,
right? They did that a long time ago.
And then over time, we stopped doing
that because it just didn't feel like a
good use of our time, and we felt that
reviewing the high-level language was
much more useful and much more
productive and led to better outcome.
And I think that's more or less where
we're going to end up with AI-powered
software building is where we're going
to look at a lot of the code that gets
generated almost like it is this
assembly code, right? It is an
implementation detail, and we want to be
reviewing and paying attention to is the
specification, right? Is the writing of
what should the software do and how are
we checking it does that? That's key in
terms of spec-driven development is how
are we checking what the software is
supposed to do and how did we provide
that in the first place? Is that the key
goal? Like, can you maybe take a step
back now and explain what is spec-driven
development from your perspective? Yeah,
good to take a step back on that, for
sure.
I think, you know, as long as we've been
building software as an organizational
thing, right? As a team sport, part of
that has been figuring out what should
the software do and writing that down.
And sometimes we've written that down as
formal documents, sometimes we've
written that down as a series of
tickets, sometimes we've written that
down as a bunch of napkin sketches and
some stuff on a whiteboard. And all of
those things are specifications.
And I think in this new era of AI, what
we're finding is that writing down what
your software can do, and And going to
call it this word specification. That
implies a level of formality that
doesn't necessarily require, but it is a
description that is as crisp as it needs
to be about what the software can do and
what a successful piece of software
looks like. And then once we have that
artifact, then we can start using that
to do two things. One of them is build
the software, often with an AI assisted
process. And if you look at the
specification-driven development flow in
something like Kiro, this is an agentic
process that takes that specification,
starts building it with code. Then the
other thing that we can do with that
specification is build tests. And this
is where techniques like property-based
testing come in are super powerful. I
can extract properties from that
specification and build tests that
assert that those properties are true
about the piece of code that I've built.
But crucially, that specification isn't
a static artifact. As I build the code,
as I test the code, as I talk to
customers, as I talk to my business, as
I listen to the various stakeholders,
I'm going to keep improving that
specification. I'm going to clarify it.
Maybe I'm going to generalize it in some
ways. Maybe I'm going to make some
pieces of it much more specific. Maybe
I'm going to add in some code snippets
or UI marks and improve that
specification. And then that is going to
feed into improving the code and
improving the tests. And so this is a
iterative software development approach,
a short-term iterative software
development approach, but one that is
very explicit about writing down the
goals of what it is that we're trying to
build and then really using AI tools to
accelerate the building of that. So you
mentioned Kiro. Can you just talk to our
audience about what Kiro is?
Yeah, so Kiro is essentially three
things. It's an IDE, it's a CLI, a
command line interface, and most
importantly, it's a set of agents that
we've built here at Amazon that we use
for our internal development and we can
talk about some of our successes with
that and is available to customers too.
It's a set of tools for agentic
development. It supports the vibe coding
mode, it supports the CLI-based
step-by-step mode, but most importantly
in my mind, it supports this
specification-driven
development approach where alongside the
Kiro agent inside the Kiro IDE, you
develop a specification of the software
and you use that specification to
develop the software, use that
specification to build the tests powered
by those Kiro agents, and then that
feeds back, then you go out to the
world, you show the world your software,
and then you feed that back into
improving and sharpening that
specification.
There are a lot of tools out there
today. So I'm just curious what led you
to build a new one?
I think we had two pieces of vision
there. One of them was when we started
this journey of building Kiro and
building the Kiro agents, the world was
starting to move on from the kind of
using AI as smart autocomplete, which
was a nice interim step, to this vibe
coding mode of prompt-by-prompt
development. And we had used that
internally at Amazon and at AWS. And
what we were finding with that
prompt-by-prompt development is it it
felt really good early on, but it wasn't
scaling super well to more complex
codebases. And most importantly, it
wasn't scaling well over time, right?
Like we would build software
prompt-by-prompt, then we would write a
prompt to add a feature and it would go
and undo a bunch of the stuff that it
had done. It sort of forgotten
requirements from earlier on. And that
got a bunch of us in different ways
thinking about what if we could solve
that requirement over time problem? And
that's where we ended up with
specification-driven development of
saying, "Hey, let's write down all of
these requirements. Let's keep all of
these requirements handy. So as we
iterate on a piece of software, we can
refer back to them and say, 'Does this
piece of software still meet these other
things that we were doing?'" Right? It's
like having a map rather than having
turn-by-turn directions. So building
Kiro allowed us to really experiment
with and then really invest in the
specification-driven development. The
other thing, the other investment that
we've been making is in code reasoning
and neurosymbolic AI where we use
symbolic tools, solvers, and so on,
these more formal side of AI to reason
about code. And we wanted to bring the
power of those tools to software
developers in an easier way too. And by
building those tools into Kiro where
they can do things like power some of
our work on property-based testing, we
can bring the power of code reasoning
tools and symbolic reasoning tools to
programmers in a way that it doesn't
require them to be experts in formal
methods or automated reasoning and so
on. Could you take an example and walk
us through the steps of how somebody
would use Kiro? And I'm really curious
about an example of a property-based
test that you mentioned a couple of
times too.
Yeah, let's pick an example. One of our
recent releases, maybe not that recent
anymore. We built Aurora DB SQL, right?
This great scalable, multi-region
active-active SQL database. And what the
team realized that customers needed was
a set of drivers to make that database
easier to use from within Java. So we
could write a specification that said,
"Here's the driver that we need to
build. Here are the properties that it
needs to have. Here are the ways that
customers should interact with it." Sort
of an API sketch. And then use that
property, that flow to generate the
implementation of that driver. And then
when we think about a property-based
test, a property-based test would take
out something from the specification
like every connection attempt contains
an authorization token. And then build a
test that tests in an automated way lots
and lots and lots of permutations of
using the driver's API and makes sure
that that property of every attempt to
connect contains an authorization token
is always true no matter what
permutations of the APIs. Either I put
things in the API and I get a valid
request out or I put things in the API
and I get a helpful failure or helpful
error message out. And so that's quite a
bit in the small. It's a relatively
modest-sized project, but a very useful
one.
Another bigger project is that we have
been building a new fundamental piece of
our inference infrastructure also using
Kiro, also using specification-driven
development. And that's more of the kind
of cloud service type rather than end
driver. And so there the specification
is about this is a cloud service that
does these things, has this
architecture, it has this API, it's
written in Rust, and so we want to use
all safe code for example, and then
generate the code from that. And then we
get these specifications or properties
again, like if a customer calls this
API, either it passes on the request in
this form or routes the request in this
form or it gives the customer a useful
400 or 500 error message. And what the
property-based test will do and what
makes it so interesting is it isn't
going to test five or six cases like a
human developer might. It is in an
automated way going to go off and test
hundreds, thousands, millions of
different API permutations and make sure
that property holds in all of them.
Can you maybe walk us through the stages
potentially for based on some of the
things you said that potentially may not
be applicable to all projects, but when
I think of the SDLC and from some of the
pointers you had, the spec is the first
thing, but could you use AI to refine
the spec is the question. Then what
about the architecture, documentation,
the design documentation, the code gen
will follow that, and then talk about
code review too. You did say the
generated code, you could start thinking
of it really as assembly and not really
necessary to read it, but would you
still potentially get a different model
perhaps to validate the code by some
form of code review? You mentioned a lot
about test, but maybe just walk us
through all the stages for a complex
project and what would you then not
necessarily do for a simpler project?
Well, I think step one for every project
is figuring out what problem you're
trying to solve and for who, right? Like
who is the customer? What do they need?
What are the requirements of the
business? And AI helps there. It can
help me pull in a bunch of requirements.
It can help me write documents. It can
help me figure out what questions I need
to ask different stakeholders, but
doesn't fundamentally change that step
of the software life cycle. And that's
going to vary, right? If I'm writing a
super important piece of code for a new
AWS service, I'm going to go wide with
that. I'm going to talk to a bunch of
people. I'm going to really understand
the economics of that. If I'm just
hacking on a software project, that's
something I'm going to do in my head in
a couple of minutes. And then we have
the step of writing down the initial
version, let me say, of the
specification. And then yeah, I mean, I
can do that manually or I can have the
AI help me with that. That can be
I start off with develop a specification
based on these prompts, based on these
customer use cases, based on these
customer anecdotes. And then I can read
that specification and say, "Well, no,
that's not quite what I meant. Let's
iterate on that together." And so that
can be anything from me writing it down
all at once to kind of vibe specifying,
right? Like, "Hey, I'm going to go piece
by piece. I'm going to go anecdote by
anecdote and check that those meet in
the specification." But what's important
is that I'm reading that specification.
I'm thinking about it. Is it the right
thing? And it's only an initial
specification. So we're going to close
the loop on that in a second. Then,
again working with the AI, I am going to
turn that specification into a set of
design decisions, right? Like is this a
web service? Is this a microservice? Is
this a library? Is it a UI application?
Is it a web application? Right? Those
are important design choices that again
are going to be driven by the needs of
the business, needs of the problem I'm
trying to solve. They aren't kinds of
decisions that the AI can make for me.
They're decisions I'm making based on my
understanding of the problem I'm trying
to solve. Then we're going to make a
bunch of implementation choices. I'm
going to choose a programming language.
Maybe I'm going to choose some
frameworks. Maybe I'm going to choose
some libraries, right? If I'm building a
web app, I'm probably going to use
TypeScript. If I'm building a new
component for an AWS service, I'm
probably going to use Rust. If I'm
building a library for people to consume
in Python, I'm probably going to use
Python. If I'm doing some AI science and
data analysis, maybe I'm going to use
Python again. What frameworks do I want?
Do I want to use internal or external
frameworks? Do I want to use open source
things? So then I've got my
specification. I've got this high-level
description of my software design. And
then I've got this low-level description
of these implementation choices. Then
I'm going to step into, okay, let me go
and generate the code, the first
versions of the code, and the first
versions of the tests. And I'm going to
do that working with the agent step by
step, stepping through the
specification, and at each step making
sure that I'm moving forward and
implementing more and more of the
specification as it comes. And then we
get to the crucial part where I've
generated the code. It's passing all of
the tests. And now I'm going to see does
it actually meet the needs of the
customer or business? Does it actually
do the thing that I'm building this
software system to do? And maybe it does
initially, but then people will say,
"Well, it'd be really cool if you had a
feature to do this thing." Or be really
cool if this button was over there. Or
be really cool if you redesigned this to
be clearer in some way. And then I loop
back. I loop back to that specification.
I loop back to those design choices, and
I iteratively change them, and then we
rebuild the code alongside the agent. We
rebuild the tests alongside the agent,
and then run the software in production
again. And so it remains this iterative
process, but it's an iterative process
where the core goal of the iteration is
keeping a specification up to date. And
downstream of that is keeping code and
tests and so on up to date.
Another benefit from I got from what you
said is it gives you an ability to check
along the way rather than just handing
off the spec to the AI and then getting
the final code generated. You're
actually have a checkpoint where you
read the design doc that is generated,
make sure it's correct, or any details
of the spec itself, and make sure it's
correct, and so on. Is that right? Yeah,
that's exactly right. And how long you
let the AI run probably varies from
application to application and goal to
goal, but it does give you this
checkpoint of checking in of am I headed
in the right direction? Am I driving to
the right place? So that you get into an
autonomous taxi, and you say, "I want to
go to this place." And you watch out the
window and see are we actually going
there? Or maybe I've changed my opinion,
and I want to go somewhere else. But
yeah, and it does give you these interim
steps of, "Okay, before I go off and
generate all this code and spend all of
this time and spend all of these tokens,
am I actually building something that is
going to solve my customers' problems?"
A question about the models that you
use. Is there any benefit that you've
observed from maybe using a different
model for some of those stages, perhaps
for code review?
Yeah, so that's really interesting. So
actually we need to talk about the code
review question. I think tentatively
yes, right? It certainly is useful to
have, at this moment with the technology
where we are, and things are moving so
quickly that this might not be true by
the end of the week. But from what I've
seen at this moment, it's really useful
to have, let's say, a separate agent
doing things like code review rather
than letting the code builder
self-supervise. And so you want this
agent that's going to look at the code
as an artifact and say, "Is it meeting
my goals? Is it well-designed? Does it
have good internal APIs?" All of these
things that we think add up to good code
maintainability over time. So a
different agent, differently prompted,
an agent with different goals, and
that's what's important for the agents.
Is it helpful to use a different model
for that? I think tentatively yes again.
I think we've seen some good indications
that doing that code review with models
of different sizes or models of
different capabilities is useful, but I
wouldn't say that's anywhere near as
useful as the sort of fundamental
multi-agent architecture of saying,
"Hey, I want my code review to be done
by an agent whose goal it is to drive
for great code quality rather than the
agent whose goal it is to implement the
specification and build the code
initially.
Earlier we talked about how you came up
with this methodology. Do you happen to
have a story where you can compare and
contrast projects that were built wipe
coded versus falling a spec driven
methodology?
I don't know if we've done any kind of
side-by-side
between wipe coding and spec driven
development. But what we have found is
let me say that Amazon has a very, let's
say, service-oriented architecture, kind
of microservice architecture, and we
have literally thousands of services
within the company that provide certain
things. And as we've adopted AI, what
we've heard from the teams that own
those services is they really started
with this kind of wipe coding. And what
they were finding was they would pull
their code base into an IDE. They would
prompt for a change. Often they would
see that change successfully
implemented, but they would see also a
regression. At the same time, the AI
would kind of forget one of the things,
properties about the code, and be like,
"Well, I've optimized this, but that
breaks the API and makes the service not
work anymore." And so what we're seeing
internally at Amazon is going through
the process of I've got the service
code. I'm going to extract from that a
specification, even if it is a kind of
method-by-method code-to-text process,
and then I'm going to use that
specification in a spec driven
development flow makes that agent that
is building the next feature much better
at not undoing goodness of the past. And
a separate agent that's building tests
much better at thinking about which
tests should it build. And so I don't
think we've done a lot of side-by-side,
but I think what we have found as teams
have embraced specification driven
development, that specification
abstraction is a step that helps them
move a lot faster because it stops this
two step forward, one step back dynamic
that can happen with existing code bases
with wipe coding.
I think that's a good point, and we'll
come back to that. I just talked a
little bit more about providing context.
But before that, I'm curious. So spec
driven is a methodology Amazon built
Kiro, but I'm sure spec driven could be
applied to other agentic ideas. Is that
a fair assumption? Oh yeah, absolutely.
It's a methodology that you can use with
any of the popular tools. It's not as
ergonomic as we've tried to make it in
Kiro, but it's a methodology with
general goodness. So one we recommend to
our teams who are building software,
whatever tools they use. Thanks, Mike.
Let's go back to providing the context.
I think you brought up a good point is
that unless the spec itself or what you
told the LLM had the context of the
code, there were always regressions. Can
we generalize that? Is it then true that
wipe coding is more effective for new
projects or for open source projects?
I don't know about open source, but I
think we have seen, at least
anecdotally, that if you build a code
base with AI from the beginning, the AI
finds that code easier to understand.
Why that is, I don't really know, but
anecdotally that is true from my
experience and similar to what I hear
from my colleagues. I'll also say that
for me the easy and fun feeling of this
kind of pure wipe coding
works best in the kind of green field
new project situation. But as soon as I
have a significant existing code base
that I'm working on, then I don't find I
get as much of a benefit from that kind
of interaction. And so yeah, I would say
that that wipe coding flow is just
maximally awesome and productive for
getting from nothing to a great first
prototype, but after that, it is less
scalable. It kind of Peters out, right?
Whereas the specification flow loads a
little bit more work up front, and so
there's no hiding that. But what you get
out of that is a much more sustainable
ongoing process, an ongoing process that
is much easier to maintain, much easier
to iterate on, much easier to add
features to without regressions, much
easier to get great test coverage, much
easier to get great QA coverage. And so
by loading a little bit more work, not a
huge amount more work, but a little bit
more work at the beginning, what you end
up with is a process that doesn't drop
off, right? A process that remains
effective and productive over the long
term.
So in terms of context, you talked about
extracting the context and having that
provided as part of the spec. But, is
that sufficient? I mean, the code base
could be pretty large. You certainly
Yeah. do that all the time. What other
ways are there of providing context? I
really like that question, and I think
for two reasons. Like, one of them is I
think in a lot of ways 2026 is the year
of thinking about context management for
AI agents. It really has become one of
the most important problems in the world
of agent building. So, this is something
that everyone across the industry is
going a bunch of thought to and bunch of
investment in this year. But then if we
think about, okay, how do we think about
that in this particular case of software
building? And what's really interesting
to me is so many of the techniques that
we've developed to make software and
code bases understandable to humans also
work really well in this context, right?
Like, we have always, you know, from the
early days of kind of structured
programming kind of going all the way
back to, you know, 60 years ago thought
about
interfaces? How do we build modularity?
How do we extract functionality into
libraries? How do we extract
functionality behind APIs? You know,
whether that's a library API or a local
service API or remote microservice API.
You know, we have made software modular.
We've we've built APIs. We've built uh
contracts. We've built protocols, right?
These are all ways to take a extremely
complex piece of software, limit the
interactions, and allow us as humans to
reason about the way that that, you
know, piece of software works. And in a
lot of ways, what makes the difference
between long-term successful software
and unsuccessful long-term software is
their ability to be built in a way that
they can evolve without every change
being able to change everything about
the way they work. And that's been what
has driven the popularity of of
service-oriented and microservice
architecture. What's driven the
popularity of libraries and
modularization for the whole of the
history of software. And so, we can kind
of think about that, well, in AI, also
what we need to manage the context and
help an AI understand our code base is
modularity. Is good design. Is good
APIs. Is good documentation of the APIs
and their contracts and and what they
mean and what you can assume and what
you can depend on.
And then once you've gotten that, then
you can layer on top things like
semantic search. Right? I'm looking for
the library method that does this. Well,
here it is. And so, I don't have to
understand everything about the entire
system. I can say this library call
takes these inputs and has this effect
on the system. And so, I can reason, you
know, more locally about the behavior of
the system. And so, for me, kind of
context management for for software
agents is very much like context
management for human developers is
converting the impossible problem at
scale of reasoning about every line of
code in the system and their
interactions into this more local
reasoning thing of like, can I think
about this one library call, this one
change? And the more that we can design
our software to make changes as local as
possible, the less context you need to
successfully make changes, the more you
can well test changes, and the more
productive you can be. And I think
that's true of of AI agents just as it
has been true of humans over you know,
six plus decades of of software
engineering practice. So, you mentioned
one way of I guess two ways. One was
extracting context into the spec and
then semantic search where you
potentially have to create vectors for
bunch of code in your code base. What
else is there that you've experimented
with? Do you have any guidance on
somebody that is getting started now in
this area, what they should do?
Yeah, I mean, I think there's some
really interesting work going on around
indexing code bases and around code
understanding and, you know, extracting
understanding from code bases. But what
I would encourage people to do who are
starting out and are getting into this
kind of coding
is
to you know, think about
software design and think about internal
interfaces. You know, think about types.
Think about APIs. And think about
building your software in a way that
well encapsulates
the functionality of each component. And
that makes it much easier when you say,
you know, to the AI or you you change
the specification to find the lines of
code that are going to do things, right?
Like, it's you know, hey, UI.ts you
know, TS or whatever rather than, hey,
this is just spread out through my code
base. I can go and find the lines of
code. I can go and change the lines of
code, and they are as local as possible.
And so, you know, one of the things to
maybe optimize for and pay attention to
as you're getting started with this is
you look at I'm going to make a change
to my specification, maybe to add a
small feature. How many of the modules
of my system does the the AI need to
touch to make that
to make that happen? And if it has to
touch every module in my system, well,
then I've got a design problem that is
going to make my AI-driven development
less productive over time. You know, if
it can make a a small feature change by
touching, you know, one or two of the
modules in my one or two of the
libraries, one or two of the services,
however I affected things, well, then
I've got a design that is likely to work
over the long term and and scale up well
without, you know, blowing up context
windows, without requiring, you know,
sophisticated techniques to index and so
on. And so, if I'm seeing that number go
up, that kind of complete or number of
modules I have to to change to build a a
feature or or to add some capability go
up over time, maybe that's time to step
back and then work with the AI to do
some refactoring, to kind of tease apart
modules, to tease apart APIs. And the
good news is that, you know, AIs and you
know, these agents and especially, you
know, once you've invested in great
testing, they're extremely powerful at
doing, you know, refactoring tasks.
Let's talk about your comment on blowing
up
context windows. When does that happen?
And a related question is, when is there
too much context which actually harms
outcomes?
You know, this varies model to model,
and it has become less of a problem as
we've had, you know, some slightly
better you know, better model
capabilities. But it is still a real
problem.
Right? And so, you know, if I go into a
coffee shop and they say, "What would
you like to drink?" And I say, "Well, I
would like a latte." And by the way,
it's also 18° outside and the Seahawks
won yesterday and, you know, not only is
that going to waste a bunch of time, but
it is going to confuse the person who,
you know, it's like, "Why is this
relevant? Why are you telling me all of
these things?" Is there some way that
you want me to customize your drink
based on all of this extra information?
And so, it confuses humans. And I think,
you know, almost by analogy. And it's a
little bit risky to reason by analogy
with AI, but almost by analogy, putting
a bunch of irrelevant stuff into a
context window makes those AI outcomes
worse. And so, you know, this is where,
you know, context management becomes so
important. And there are two aspects of
it. One of them is all of that design
and modularity stuff that I I just
talked about. And the other is the AI
tool, whether that's Kiro or one of the
many other AI-powered development tools,
have to do, you know, have to manage
what's in the context window, making
sure that there is enough context to
give the AI the power to at least
discover what it should be doing. But
there shouldn't be too much context. If
it contains a bunch of irrelevant noise,
we're going to have a worse outcome.
You know, and so, if you think about
like, what do agents do? Well, one of
the things that AI agents do is build
their own context window through a
process of discovery. They'll go and
read that file, search this index,
search, you know, use this MCP tool to
do a semantic search over the
documentation, and try and build their
own context window. And again, one of
the things that makes agent development
challenging is making sure they build
their context window as reliably as
possible, containing as high a ratio of
relevant to to irrelevant information as
possible. And so, there are kinds of
three things there. There's how do I
build my code base and maintain my code
base to make it kind of context friendly
for humans and agents. How do I as
somebody who's building development
tools think about, you know, context
management. And then how do I as a
developer of agents more generally think
about guiding those agents to build
their context windows effectively. And
then, you know, the tools I give to the
agents, what do they return? the right
stuff? Do they give the agent the
ability to request only the facts it
needs and so on? What about the process
to make sure that the way you provide
the context, the source of that is if
it's not the code directly is kept up to
date. Is that something outside of the
dev process or it's kind of inbuilt
there? Yeah, you know, and this has
been, again, not a new problem in the
world of software. How do I I keep my
documentation up to date? And you know,
one of the real challenges of the kind
of pre-AI era is is how do I keep my
requirements and specification up to
date? And specification-driven
development has made made that much
easier by making, you know, everything
flow down from the specification and,
you know, has helped with that
specification freshness problem a huge
amount. But there's still a
documentation freshness problem. Well,
how do I keep my documentation up to
date? What I did in the previous AI era
is, you know, I would spend time from my
development tool or technical writers
who would, you know, look for changes in
the code and go off and update
documentation. Now, I can fact ex- you
know, very effectively accelerate that
process with AI and have, you know, an
agent in my kind of set of agents that's
doing my helping me with my software
development process that is going off
and keeping my documentation up to date,
keeping my read me up to date, keeping
those API docs up to date. And, you
know, that feeds back into the next
round of my process where I want to make
a change. How do I know that that API
doc is up to date? Because I have
continuously kept it up to date as part
of my software development flow.
You know, and so
even when I'm vibe coding, even when I'm
not doing the kind of specification
development process, I always make sure
that my prompts or my steering document
are directing the agents to keep a read
me up to date or keep a piece of
documentation up to date, both for my
reference as a human and my customer's
reference as they use my software, but
also for the reference of the agent
itself as it makes the next set of
steps. Thanks, Mark. And now I'd like to
spend a little bit of time on how do you
make sure that the configuration and the
model itself is effective? Initially,
you roll this out to the team and now
the core group that's maintaining the
config, the contacts, the different
workflows that somebody has to do, how
do they keep them up to date? So, let's
say there's a new model that comes
along. How do you make sure that it
hasn't regressed the flow in any form or
fashion?
Yeah, and so the I think the formal
answer to that is, you know, we have an
evaluation process. And that's where,
you know, we will take an agentic
workload and probably starting off
offline, run a bunch of examples through
a new model or a new configuration or a
new prompt and compare the success of
the old versus the new. And that could
be with a human looking at that, that
could be looking at are the tests
passing, it could be looking at
acceptance rate, or it could be using a
pattern like LLM as a judge where it
uses another agent essentially to rate
the agent outputs and say these ones are
better and these ones are worse. The
next step of that and and and the one
that I think is is actually most
powerful is online evaluation where,
okay, I'm going to start experimenting
with this new model in production, kind
of AB testing. I'm going to send it 5%
of traffic. I'm going to send it 10% of
traffic. And then I'm going to feed back
all of my success signals, whether those
are LLM as a judge, whether that's human
feedback, whether that's latency
information, test success rate, to look
at am I doing better with this new
version? If it looks like I'm doing
better, if those those initial
experiments are looking good, well, I'm
going to ramp that up. Eventually, I'm
going to get that up to 100% and then
I'm going to be ready to do, you know,
do the next experiment.
And then continuously in production, I'm
going to continuously be evaluating the
outcomes of my agent. Again, the metrics
I use for that depend on the task and
I'm going to know over time is my
success rate good? And, you know, if my
success rate suddenly changes for
whatever reason or trends downwards,
well, then I need to understand why that
is. Maybe my tasks have changed. Maybe
my customer's needs have changed. Maybe
I have some bad piece of context. Maybe
that read me contains some false, you
know, information that's that's leading
my agents off in the wrong direction.
But, you know, the really key thing here
is to have from the agent builder's
perspective and and here I'm I'm not
talking about, you know, the the IDE
user, they don't need to really worry
about this stuff, but me as an agent
builder, I need to think about how do I
have a robust set of evaluations so I
can run a really data-driven improvement
process around around agents, around the
models, around the prompts, around the
context, around the way the context is
managed. And the more I do that, well,
the better a quality product I can offer
to my customers, the more reliable it
will be, but it also helps me do things
like, hey, I'm doing something with a
really big model today. Can I lower my
latency by using a smaller model?
Answering that question in isolation,
man, that's next to impossible.
Answering that question when I have a
robust set of evaluators is much easier.
And so, this is a process for agent
builders, but it really goes back to the
beginning of the whole question of you
know, what are we trying to achieve?
What is the outcome that we want? You
know, what do our customers need and
what does our business need?
What is the outcome and then what is the
success rate? But maybe just
specifically what kind of things should
team be measuring? Should they be
measuring bug rates? You know, is there
human correction needed during human
code reviews? Do should they be
measuring the divergence of the code
from the spec? You know, could you share
some of those thoughts on what metrics
team should focus on?
Again, like the most important ones are
the end-to-end ones. You know, are
customers seeing bugs in production? Are
customers seeing regressions in
production? Are, you know, are customers
happy with the in-production
performance? Now, those are the most
important metrics. They're also the
hardest to measure. They're also the
ones with the highest risk because we
want to catch things before customers
are reporting bugs in production. And
so, you know, we're we're going to
choose some earlier in the process kind
of proxies for those metrics. And that's
where, you know, am I seeing failures in
regression tests, for example? What is
the test rate of failures in regression
tests? Am I seeing a Yeah, you know, if
I'm using human code review, am I seeing
a good pass rate for that human code
review? If I'm using a separate code
review agent, am I seeing a good pass
rate for that code review agent? Is it
giving me good success? If I'm using a,
you know, pen testing agent like, you
know, the one that we announced at at
re:Invent that does kind of last-mile
security testing, is that finding, you
know, security bugs before things go
into production? And so, if I'm seeing
bugs being caught at my sort of last
pre-production milestone, I know
something's not going well earlier on in
my software development process. And
that could be an inadequate kind of
early in the software life cycle
testing. It could be a symptom of bad
design and interfaces. It could maybe be
a symptom of some bad implementation
choices I need to go and fix. Or it
could be a misalignment between the
requirements of the tests that are going
into the test and the requirements that
are going into the software building
process. You know, and so if if one of
these things says
you need to return a a result to the
customer within 10 milliseconds and the
other one says 10 seconds, well,
obviously I'm going to have failures.
And so, there's this tension in these
metrics of the most valuable metrics are
the ones all the way at the end of my
software development life cycle because
they are what I really care about,
they're what my customers see, but
that's the most expensive place and so I
want to push as much of that, you know,
catching of things in those metrics sort
of left in my pipeline as possible.
Again, classic idea of software
engineering, right? Catch bugs early.
You know, we've been software engineers
have been saying that for for four or
five decades and that hasn't changed.
Thanks, Mark. Now, let's talk more about
how do you roll this out to the team?
Are there any prerequisites? Is there a
mind shift that has to happen? Or do you
just have a meeting, you introduce the
tool and tell everyone, hey, go use it?
Yeah, I mean, I think that varies. I
think the biggest prerequisite is almost
cultural, right? Too. So, what we've
seen with with adoption of of new
development practices is you need a team
that has, you know, great understanding
of their customer and business and high
standards, right? You can't accept, I
don't know, slop, I guess is the term
that people use these days, right? We
don't want that in our software
processes. But we also need folks and
see the fastest transformation that have
great curiosity, who are really
interested in picking up new things and,
you know, great bias for action of like,
hey, we're going to go off and and try
stuff and and experiment with stuff. And
so, it's that tension, I think, within
teams that I've seen really drive
success here. Is the teams are like,
well, we're going to go off and we're
going to try new things and we're really
interested in learning and trying and
adopting new tools, but at the same time
we're not going to settle for bad
outcomes for our customers, for our
business, for our engineering teams.
And, you know, when you put those two
things together, I think that's really
where where magic happens.
You know, beyond that kind of cultural
goodness, there is a,
you know, we also shouldn't expect that
teams can pick up a new tool and know
immediately how to use them well, right?
You you need this kind of communication
and sharing of saying, hey, we've tried
it this way, these are the things we
learned, you know, these are the things
that we want to pass on to you. You want
to bake those into communication that
that that you have between your teams.
And then if you're building tools, you
want to bake those lessons into your
tools. And so again, I think another
piece of success is making sure that as
a team learns how to use the tools
better or to improve the tools, the
whole organization learns. And ideally,
you know, the whole world learns and we
can kind of drive everything forward.
And sometimes that's big learnings of
saying, "Hey, we want to introduce
specification driven development because
we've learned that that scales better
than, you know, prompt by prompt vibe
coding." And sometimes it's little
things of saying, "Hey, we found that
indexing our code this way or
structuring our code this way works
really well. We found, for example,
concretely internally at Amazon that
building AI, you know, using AI powered
development with a language like Rust
with its strong type system and a bunch
of compile time checking is really,
really useful and helps accelerate
development by catching bugs earlier in
the pipeline." And so that's a message
that we want to send out to our teams
and say, you know, Rust works well.
TypeScript works pretty well. You know,
the type annotations in Python, they're
worth investing in. And, you know, it's
so it is that spreading of learning
across an organization that is is super
important. And then maybe the the last
thought on that is, "Wow, you know, no
surprise to anybody, this whole world of
AI is is moving so fast, right? There
are new techniques, there are new tools
there pretty seemingly every day and
every week."
One of the things that you need to
balance for success is, you know, you
want your teams to be paying attention
to those new tools, to be curious about
them. But you also can't afford to go
and chase, you know, every week's trend
day-to-day. And so there's a balance to
be found there of we want to adopt new
stuff, we want to adopt the best things
quickly, but we don't want to spend all
of our time just thrashing on trying the
latest, you know, the latest and
greatest or or most fashionable tool of
the moment. So yeah, there's a lot to
put together into organizational
success.
So certainly, of course, curiosity is
critical but bias for action seems to be
more important based on your comment.
Though with this specifically, with AI
specifically, there's a little bit of
fear as well. How do you address that?
What kind of fear? Can you say more
about the fears?
>> I mean, with AI doing more and more, is
different things expected of the
developer or less expected of the
developer as we proceed on this journey?
Well, you know, I think that the job of
software development and, you know, more
broadly the job of of software
engineering is changing. And our jobs
are going to be very different in, you
know, 2, 5, 10 years from from the jobs
that they are today. And, you know, with
any major change, there is going to come
uncertainty. People are going to to
think about, you know, "What does this
change mean for me and and for the
reasons that I went into this field and
and the things that I love about this
kind of work." And, you know, I'm super
optimistic about that, right? I think
AI powered development is
freeing us up to spend more time on the
things that matter.
And, you know, whether those things that
matter are, you know, being closer to
customers, being closer to the business,
really understanding the big picture of
the systems we're building, or, you
know, getting really deep on the you
know, various parts of of the design,
getting really deep on protocols,
getting really deep on efficiency. And,
you know, less time on the
sort of undifferentiated busy work of
building. So yeah, I mean, it's a time
of really fast change in the industry
and I think that is always going to come
with some level of anxiety. You know,
I'm super optimistic that it is going
to, you know, free us up to do a a job
that is is more fulfilling and more
valuable. And, you know, we've seen over
decades, you know, how powerful a
economic force software has been. And
over decades and, you know, the whole
lifetime of software, it has been supply
constrained. The the economic impact of
of software has been constrained by how
much great software we can build. And,
you know, I strongly believe that if we
can drive down the cost of software
development with AI tools by 10x,
there's going to be at least 10x
economic impact of software, if not 100x
economic impact of software. And so, you
know, I think software and and software
engineering is going to be even more
important in the future than it is
today.
But it is going to be a different job.
It's going to have, you know, different
things and and we're going to need to
optimize in in different ways. And I
think it's very reasonable for people to
feel challenged by that. I think it's
very reasonable for people to reflect
and say, "Hey, what does this this mean
for me?" You know, I can't say anything
other than personally, as someone who's
been excited and passionate about
technology, I think the future is is
just super exciting.
Thanks, Mark. So starting to wrap up
now, a couple of questions. What about
the steps beyond the development of the
software? What about deployment,
incident management, etc.? Is that tied
to anything that you're thinking of with
Kiro or, you know, beyond that in AWS?
So, you know, at re:Invent back in
December, we announced our our DevOps
agent, which is an agent that is
designed for, you know, doing these
DevOps things in the cloud, helping out
with incidents, helping out with
tickets, helping out with infrastructure
as a service maintenance, and so on. So
yeah, another part of the work that
software teams do.
We announced our security agent, which,
you know, is for for helping out with
that that pen testing and and other
parts of the kind of security testing
life cycle.
You know, we have AWS Transform, which
is a set of agents for, you know, taking
moving systems from one implementation
to another, you know, whether that is
small patching tasks like, "Hey, I want
to to pick up the latest version of
Java." to major software kind of
re-architectures of, you know, "I want
to get off a mainframe and get into the
cloud." And so, you know, it is vastly
beyond just the work of building
software. We're going to use agents to
accelerate the deployment of software,
to simplify the operations of software,
to simplify, you know, software
maintenance. And that's a huge one,
right? I don't I don't know many
software engineers who are excited
about, you know, making sure I can
migrate from Java 11 to Java 17 or or
what it 21 or whatever the latest one is
these days. But it's critical. It's
critical work for security, for
efficiency, for all of these, you know,
other things. And so, you know, that's
going to be a big one. The ability to
change back-end implementations
much more easily and with lower risk is
is huge for engineering teams, right?
Like Hey, I have all of this legacy. I
built these things. Maybe I wrote all
this code in Fortran. It is the crown
jewel of my organization because it's
the only expression of my business
logic. You know, how do I bring that
into a modern implementation? How do I
bring that into a modern architecture?
Again, you know, this is something that
AI is really going to power for us.
Testing, validation, UI testing. You
know, there's so much of of the process
around software. You know, even updating
tickets, all of these things.
I think
you know, these are areas that we're
investing in heavily in AWS because, you
know, we have paid a bunch of attention
to where, you know, software developers
both internally and in our customers
actually spending their time, software
teams and organizations are spending
their time. But they're not as shiny and
cool as as software building. And so,
you know, all the buzz is around, you
know, here's a thing that helps me write
more code more quickly. And I think
that's okay, but really the big picture
is here's something that allows me as an
software organization, as a leader of a
software organization, or to deliver
value to my customers more quickly and
more reliably. And that's going to take
much more than just writing more code.
But still, you are writing code as
you're building these agents. You're
writing code to build these agents. Is
there special considerations for
generating code for agents itself?
Yeah, I think that is an area that is
emerging. So if I look at the kind of
first few generations of agent building,
you know, very
you know, a bunch of Python, bunch of
kind of ad hoc techniques. It's been,
you know, very valuable. But over time,
you know, what's emerging is can we mix
in tools like symbolic reasoning? Can we
add more structure? You know, and so,
for example, we we built this really
cool set of features into Strands, which
is our agent framework called Strands
Steering, that uses a neuro-symbolic
technique combining kind of models and
symbolic reasoning to nudge agent
trajectories in in the right direction.
You know, we're seeing
more tools that close that optimization
and evaluation loop with improving tool
descriptions and so on. You know, we're
seeing tools like the policy that we
built into Agent Core, which allows you
to take a kind of plain text description
of a security constraint or an
operational constraint, turn that into a
crisp piece of authorization code in a
approvable language like Cedar, and
apply those to all of the agents.
And so, I think what we're going to
learn and and are actively learning is
how do we build software development
practices and tools that go around
agents that allow us to take advantage
of the flexibility and power of agents,
which is what we need, right? We want
our agents to be flexible. We want them
to almost be creative in their ability
to solve problems, but we also need to
do that in a way that is secure and
meets the business needs and doesn't do
things that are dangerous. And And so
policy helps balance that. Strand
steering helps balance that. You know,
we also need to to reduce cost and and
that's where things like model
customization come in. And so agent
building, you know, is in this this
super exciting moment of a huge amount
of both, you know, existing impact, but
also a massive amount of innovation. And
so, you know, I think what we're going
to see is over the next few years
building reliable agents is going to
become even easier and easier and
building cost-effective agents with
great ROI is going to be easier. And so
that's been our focus at AWS and it's
certainly a focus across the industry
of, you know, how do we take agent
building from being this fairly ad hoc
almost kind of bunch of spells to being
a real, you know, a real engineering
discipline. Thanks, Mark. So, we're
running out of time, so I won't ask you
about the stuff you mentioned a few
times, the neuro-symbolic reasoning, but
I'd love to get some references to add
to our show notes for readers. Yeah,
we'd love to share. Is there anything
that we missed today that you'd like to
spend a few minutes on?
I think the overall message for me for
software builders is
if we think about code, you know, it
encodes what it does, right? Like very,
very crisply to computers. And we
haven't historically been reliably in
the habit as software builders of
writing down why. Why is the code like
this? And I think, you know,
specification-driven development gets
its power from making the why is the
code like this explicit both to humans
and to models. And so I think that is
going to be this huge transformation we
see in software is that the details of
the how are going to
maybe be less valuable. And the
artifacts explaining the why, why is the
software designed this way, what is it
trying to achieve, who's it trying to
achieve it for, is going to become more
and more and more valuable. That is
going to be true if you're doing
specification development. I think it's
true if you're doing vibe coding. And I
think it's going to be true of, you
know, whatever the next waves of
agent-powered or AI-powered or even, you
know, human development practices look
like.
Thanks, Mark. How can people contact you
and keep up with your work?
Check out my blog. That's brooker.co.za.
And I'm on LinkedIn and X and and and
various other social platforms. I love
to share the work that me and my team
are doing here at AWS on those
platforms. You know, always, you know,
love to hear thoughtful questions from
folks and have great discussions about
the future of software engineering.
Thank you so much, Mark. This was a very
interesting discussion on a very
interesting topic.
Great. Well, thank you and thanks for
the opportunity and and tested
conversation.
>> [music]
>> Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE Software Magazine. For more [music]
about the podcast, including other
episodes, visit our website at
se-radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
through our Slack channel at
se-radio.slack.com.
[music]
You can also email us at
team@se-radio.net.
>> [music]
>> This and all other episodes of SE Radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
License 2.5.
Thanks for listening.
>> [music]